Okay so today's דף daf is ק"א. kof alef. We begin in
the pick up in the middle of ק' עמוד ב' kof amud
bet where it says, if you look at the left-hand column between
רש"י Rashi and the גמרא Gemara it says משלי י"ב. Mishlei Yud
Bet.
And we're dealing with quotes from בן סירא Ben Sira because one
of the people that doesn't have a חלק עולם הבא chelek olam
haba according to one opinion is somebody that's קורא בספרים חיצוניים, kore
besfarim chitzonim, reads in the like apocrypha, external books, presumably books that
didn't make it into the canon but were sort of attributed with
some type of a holy significance. And then to that is added
one of the תנאים Tana'im adds even somebody who reads in בן
סירא. Ben Sira. Well, that's not in the is that in the
it's not in the
משנה, Mishnah, right? The משנה Mishnah just says רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
has קורא בספרים חיצוניים kore besfarim chitzonim and the גמרא Gemara quotes
a ברייתא Baraita of רב יוסף Rav Yosef who says even ספר
בן סירא. Sefer Ben Sira. Now of course you have to pre
and then the גמרא Gemara says, well, what's so bad about בן
סירא? Ben Sira? And then it goes through a whole thing quoting
all these verses from בן סירא Ben Sira and saying they're basically
the same type of message we have in other verses in תנ"ך.
Tanakh. So of course you have to appreciate the irony here, which
is that the גמרא Gemara is showing its complete fluency in בן
סירא Ben Sira in the middle of a discussion about your permission
to read from בן סירא. Ben Sira. So there's obviously a subtext
here, and the subtext is either that we don't rule like רב
יוסף Rav Yosef and the גמרא Gemara regularly quotes בן סירא Ben
Sira and actually even every now and then even says even says
כדכתיב, kidechtiv, which is a word that the גמרא Gemara uses for
scripture. But even to the degree that it's ruling like בן סירא,
Ben Sira, you know, the general assumption ah, ruling like רב יוסף.
Rav Yosef. The assumption is because of the גמרא's Gemara obvious fluency
with בן סירא Ben Sira which it puts on display right here
is that it means, you know, it's only if you sort of
treat it as scripture, you know, treat it as holy writ or
that you, you know, you do a learning with it that's really
prioritizing it as opposed to just, you know, it's like if you
want to read from it like you read from Ben Franklin's what
was Ben Franklin's thing? Poor Richard's Almanac or something like that, you
know, be my guest. You want to read from Confucius because you
find some wisdom in it, you know, be my guest, you know.
Don't get a as we're going to say don't get drawn, don't
assume it's somehow divinely inspired and you're going to take everything as,
you know, as holy. There's some stuff there that's either nonsense or
wrong or maybe even misleading. But like, alright, you know, like it
doesn't mean like it's אסור assur to read. Yes Michal. Wait Michal
has her hand up.
Yes. I was wondering is it קורא ב kore be ספרים sfarim
and that there is a difference between קורא את kore et and
קורא ב. kore be.
Ah, interesting. Nice point.
No no, finish, go ahead.
When it says in the גמרא Gemara קורא בספרים החיצוניים, kore basfarim
hachitzonim, you don't קורא בעיתון, kore baiton, you don't קורא בספרים, kore
basfarim, you קורא את הספר, kore et hasefer, קורא ספר. kore sefer.
So there is like a difference.
That's interesting.
That's an interesting sense. The ב bet might be indicating that.
And the other one was that the ספרים חיצוניים sfarim chitzonim connect
the תנ"ך Tanakh with the ברית חדשה Brit Chadashah and so it's
like a bridge
around
the תנ"ך Tanakh so that you because the נוצרים Nozarim try to
make a link.
Right. But I don't think that's true about all the ספרים חיצוניים
sfarim chitzonim like ספר מכבים, Sefer Maccabim, right, and others don't seem
to do that. Right. But I think it's also so it's not
just that they're sort of a lead-in, but it's I would say
it a little differently. I would say that if you're blurring the
lines, right, if you're sort of saying, oh these pseudo-biblical
books are also treated as biblical, then once you start blurring the
lines, who knows? You could also start thinking that the, you know,
that the Christian Testament or whatever. So it's not just that it
functions as a bridge, but it blurs lines. But yes, but I
appreciate the ב, bet, yeah, yeah.
And the things that are the same as in the תורה Torah
so we don't need it.
Well
right, but you know, yes. That's true. That's true. Yes Charlie, yes.
Right.
So immediately before רב יוסף Rav Yosef talking about
בן סירא Ben Sira they there's a ברייתא Baraita about that signs
off with ספרי מינים. Sifrei Minim. Is that the language that's in
the standard text? It's even in the Artscroll by the way. Right.
Well we have it switched to, you know, some have it switched
to צדוקים Tzadokim but clearly it's not צדוקים Tzadokim in this context.
Yeah it is. It is מינים, Minim, yes. Yeah so which again
often means often means, you know, Jewish-Christians and so on. Yes. Yeah.
Okay fine. Alright so let's keep on going. So let's get back
to going. So the גמרא Gemara says,
okay, אלא משום דכתיב, ela mishum dechtiv, I'll go back to that
פסוק pasuk right above where it says משלי י"ב. Mishlei Yud Bet.
So maybe it's because of the following verse in בן סירא. Ben
Sira. By the way notice דכתיב dechtiv is right even here embedded
in the whole discussion. לא תעייל דויא בלבך, Lo ta'il davya belibakh,
do not let anguish enter into your heart, דגויא גברין קטילה, dgavya
gavrin ketila, it's slain even the mightiest of men.
So דויא, davya, excuse me, that anguish has slain mightiest of men.
So the גמרא Gemara says, so what's wrong with that? שלמה אמר,
Shlomo amar, that's in משלי, Mishlei, דאגה בלב איש ישחנה, de'aga belev
ish yis-chena, or ישחנה, yis-chena, now what does that mean? What? ישחנה
yashchenah is probably in the original. We read it as ישיחנה, yesachenah,
I know. So it's the original is ישחנה, yashchenah, which is like
lay a person low, okay? So that's exactly the same like it'll
slaughter them. But now we sort of do a little play on
words, רב אמי ורב אסי, Rav Ami ve-Rav Assi, חד אמר ישיחנה
מדעתו, chad amar yesichenah mi-da'ato, remove it from like just try to
ignore it, try to just subvert, you know, right right, you know,
but try to like what's that word called? Pushing it under,
repress it or something, וחד אמר ישיחנה לאחרים. ve-chad amar yesichenah le-acherim.
No, go see a therapist and talk about it, that'll help you.
אוקיי, ואלא משום דכתיב, okay, ve-ela mishum de-chtiv, but because it's written,
so here's the problematic verse. מנע רבים מתוך ביתך, mena rabbim mi-toch
beitecha, don't have like, you know, your house as open door policy,
keep the masses out of your house. ולא הכל תביא אל ביתך,
ve-lo ha-kol tavi el beitecha, and even if you like have a
lot of friends, not everybody you have to invite home. ואתא רבי
נמי אמרה, ve-ata Rabbi nami amrah,
but you know, Rabbi said that, דתניא, de-tanya, רבי אומר, Rabbi omer,
לעולם לא ירבה אדם רעים בתוך ביתו, le-olam lo yarbe adam re'im
be-toch beito, you should not have too many people in your home,
שנאמר, she-ne'emar, איש רעים להתרועע. ish re'im lehitro'ea.
A person, a friend, להתרועע lehitro'ea here is sort of being interpreted
like to destroy, like it'll, you know, you have them in your
house, you know, not everybody is going to treat your property with
respect, you know, not everybody like, not everybody you're friendly with out
in the street means that that's the type of people that you
or at work are the type of people that you bring home.
In countries like Isaiah or in Pirkei Avot?
No, that's about people that need, yeah, that's about people that need
your help and support. This is talking about, you know, you have
a lot of work colleagues, you don't all of a sudden extend
an invitation and have them all, you know, whatever. No, it's not
talking about people that need, you know, your support. אלא משום דכתיב,
ela mishum de-chtiv, but because it's written, זלדקן קורטמן. zal dikan korteman.
First of all, that if somebody has a זל, zal, a small,
a thin beard, is a קורטמן, korteman, which apparently Rashi says means
is a, is a wise person. עבדקן, avdikan, somebody who has a
thick beard, סכסכן sachsachan
is a stupid person, okay? So דנפח בכסיה לא צחי, de-nafach be-chasei
lo tsachi,
and somebody that blows in his cup, you know, maybe to blow
it down, it's a little hot or whatever he's doing, anyway to
blow down the froth, he must obviously not be too thirsty because
if he was thirsty, he would not be spending time doing that.
אמר במה איכול לחמא, amar be-mai eichol lachma, if somebody's saying, well,
what would be a good thing, a good spread to put on
my bread, so לחמא סבינה, lachma sabineh, he obviously can't be too
hungry. Like if you're hungry, you just eat your darn bread. So
take away his bread from him, he doesn't deserve his bread. מאן
דאית ליה מעברתא דדיקניה, man de-it lei ma'avarta de-dikneh,
going back to the beard, somebody that's got like a split in
his beard, you know, sometimes like the beard sort of like comes
off at two at, you know, splits down the middle, so כולי
עלמא לא יכלי ליה, kulei alma lo yachlei lei, nobody can stand
up against him. Rashi says one explanation, one I like the best
of Rashi is like he's obviously a sly person, you know, he's
always like, you know, he's running his hands through his beard and
thinking, ooh, what am I going to do, like, you know.
So anyway, alright, so that's the foolishness, okay? So that's the problem
with Ben Sira, it's got some things it's very wise and some
things it's just foolish. Okay.
אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, מילי מעלייתא דאית ביה דרשינן להו.
milei ma'alyata de-it bei darshinan le-hu. Fine, there's some stuff that's foolish.
But the good stuff in it we can still explicate. By the
way, again, notice the words
דכתיב, de-chtiv, דרשינן, darshinan, so in the whole discussion about not doing
it and even they try to limit that point about like not
treating it like scripture, you know, they're still giving it like a
type of a weight. But just be careful about it. Okay. Now,
איתא דכתיב, ita de-chtiv,
here's a verse or whatever from Ben Sira. אשה טובה מתנה טובה,
ishah tovah matanah tovah,
a good woman is a good gift, בחיק ירא אלהים תינתן, be-cheik
yere elohim tinaten, she should be given into the bosom of a
person who fears, a man who fears God. אשה רעה צרעת לבעלה,
ishah ra'ah tsara'at le-ba'alah, a wicked woman is like a leprosy plague
to her husband. Okay, מאי תקנתיה? mai tekan-teih? Now, this seems like
the
Gemara, although before like we were having Aramaic verses from Ben Sira.
So it's not exactly clear, is the Gemara always directly quoting Ben
Sira, paraphrasing Ben Sira? But yes, here it at least seems that
the word מאי תקנתיה mai tekan-teih is a Gemara insertion. So יגרשנה
מביתו, yegarashenah mi-beito, so it sounds now we're back to the Hebrew.
So what should he do? He should divorce her or drive her
out of his house, ויתרפא מצרעתו, ve-yitrapah mi-tsara'ato,
and then he'll be healed from his plague. Okay, אשה יפה אשרי
בעלה, ishah yafah ashrei ba'alah,
a beautiful woman, praised be her husband, מספר ימיו כפליים, mispar yamav
kiflayim,
his days will be like doubled because he'll be in so much
good, you know, high quality. העלם עיניך מאשת חן, ha'alem einecha me-eshet
chen,
but you, if you know, you see a charming woman who's your
husband's wife, your husband's, your friend's wife, you know, hide your eyes
from her. That would be like, you know, this sounds also like
very much like the whole beginning of משלי Mishlei is all about,
you know, the the the seductress woman, although this, the woman seems
relatively innocent, you just as the man with the roving eye, you
might be a little bit charmed by this woman. So lest you
be ensnared במצודתה, bi-metsudatah, so actually maybe she's not so innocent, ensnared
in her net. אל תטה אצל. al tetei etsel. אל תט אצל
בעלה, al teiteitz el ba'alah, do not incline yourself to her husband's
home, don't decide you're going to spend a lot of time by
your friend's house because you're attracted to his wife. Okay, לסמוך עמו
יין ושכר, lismoach imo yayin v'sheichar,
to drink with him wine and beer, כי בתואר אשה יפה רבים
הושחתו ki b'toar isha yafa rabim hushchatu
because with the visage of a beautiful woman many have been destroyed
ועצומים כל הרוגיה v'atzumim kol harugeha and and multiple you know
many great are those that that her you know she has killed
you know obviously not intentionally whatever you know that people have as
a result gone down on the wrong path and it's led to
great destruction. רבנין רבים היו, rabnin rabim hayu, this is a long
verse. רבים היו פצעי רוכל rabim hayu pitzei rochel many are the
wounds of the of the like of the perfume merchant because he's
going and spending all this time with women and maybe he's actually
having you know sleeping with them or he's being suspected of it
and then the husbands are coming and beating him up. המרגילים לדבר
ערווה hamargilim l'dvar erva
those that accustom themselves to you know acts to forbidden sexual acts
or maybe even exposing themselves to these scenarios you know getting into
these situations כי ניצוץ מבעיר גחלת ki nitzotz mav'ir gachelet
you're just asking for trouble. It's like a spark you know on
a keg of powder keg we would say. Here it says a
spark on a ember on a smoldering ember. Maybe the smoldering ember
is a good is a good image like you know we all
like people have like the sexual you know sexual drive but maybe
they're keeping it under control you know and you expose it to
a little spark and you know that'll set off a whole conflagration.
Yes, Michael.
So I was just trying to understand, I understand the statement of
רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, the statement of רב יוסף Rav Yosef who
says מילי מעלייתא דאית בהו דרשינן milei ma'alyata d'is behu darshinan who's
in the very beginning you know you can't read it. So like
how do you make רב יוסף Rav Yosef doesn't contradict himself?
That's a good so maybe yes he is not contradicting. I didn't
recognize it was the same רב יוסף Rav Yosef and but
yeah but maybe he's exactly not contradicting. Maybe he's exact saying like
don't treat this as holy scripture you know although he didn't use
those words above but you know but identify the good stuff and
there's no problem with like reading it and recognizing the good things.
So that's an excellent point that I hadn't recognized that it's maybe
exactly רב יוסף Rav Yosef himself who's qualifying his statement. Although you'd
want the first statement to be a little clearer but maybe it
becomes clearer by juxtaposing it with the second one. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay,
ככלוב kichlov
now we're going to quote a פסוק, pasuk, this is a פסוק
pasuk in ירמיה. Yirmiyah. ככלוב
מלא עוף kichlov malei of like a like
a bird net not net a bird I don't know hut you
know filled with birds כן בתיהם מלאים מרמה ken bateihem m'lei'im mirmah
so their houses are filled with with deceit. מנע רבים מתוך ביתך
m'ne rabim mitoch beitacha so that's now going back and showing a
פסוק pasuk here that parallels what we had earlier from בן סירא,
Ben Sira,
hold you know keep the masses out of your house ולא הכל
תביא ביתך v'lo hakol tavi beitacha okay and not everybody you should
bring home. רבים יהיו דורשי שלומך rabim yihiyu dorshei shlomecha
many should be those who seek after your well-being. So you should
have a lot of friends, not telling you not to have a
lot of friends. You have them all? Okay, but just don't have
them all over. Okay? גלה סודך לאחד מאלף galei sodecha l'echad me'alef
but only you know really take into your trust one out of
a thousand. Okay? You can have a lot of friends but those
friends are not the same as confidants. משוכבת חיקך שמור פתחי פיך
mishochevet cheikecha shmor pitchi picha
from the one who sleeps in your bosom, your wife, because obviously
it's talking to the man, watch what you say. Which is really
wonderful, like okay you know only have one you know one out
of a thousand should be your confidant but don't trust your wife
necessarily. Okay, watch what you say even to your wife. אל תצר
צרת מחר al tatzar tzarot machar
do not worry about the anguish of tomorrow like oh my god
what's tomorrow going to bring, like live with all of this anxiety
כי לא תדע מה ילד יום ki lo teda ma yeled yom
now quoting a different פסוק, pasuk, you don't know what tomorrow's going
to bring. What good does it do to worry tomorrow's problems today?
You're just importing tomorrow's problems. Okay? You'll by tomorrow you can worry
about tomorrow's problems, right? The anxiety doesn't help, it's not constructive thinking.
שמא shema now of course this makes it a little more fatal
what do you call like fatalistic here שמא למחר איננו shema l'machar
eineno you know maybe you won't even live until tomorrow so what
do you have to worry about tomorrow? ונמצא מצטער על עולם שאינו
שלו v'nimtza mitzta'er al olam she'eino shelo you worry about a day
that's not even going to be yours because you're not even going
to live to see it. Okay, so I don't know if I
would exactly put it that way but you know why do you
have to worry? What good is it going to do? You're just
importing tomorrow's problems today. You know דבורה Dvorah and I like he's
she like I am like the optimist of the home and she's
the pessimist. So I say to her I say you know דבורה
Dvorah like you know I you know so so
so like okay like you know you go through every single day
you know you're always worried about you know what the possible bad
outcome like I so I just assume everything is going to be
fine so you know so it's most I'm happy most of the
time. She says yeah but then when something goes wrong like you're
surprised and I you know and I expected it. So anyway, but
okay so that's the question I still think what good does it
do? Something goes wrong it'll go wrong. I mean there's constructive planning
of possible future events. But what good does it do to have
all the anxiety right now?
Yeah, say it differently, אשר יגורתי באנו, asher yagorti banu, meaning the
very thing you worried about, it's in you, like
the whole precipitate of that thought. That's true. You're right. I was
reading רשי. Rashi. A better read of that is what you were
worrying about isn't going to materialize. You're right. I think רשי Rashi
was picking up on עולם שאינו שלו, olam she'eino shelo, like the
you know it's not even going to be your world, but you
could read it as that reality is not going to be your
reality. So what good did it do you to worry about it?
Right, I appreciate that. That's a better read. Okay. כל ימי עני
רעים. kol yemei ani ra'im. All the days of a poor person...
Yeah, we did have before. All the days, blah blah blah, so
you see that, all the days of a poor person are evil.
Okay, so that's again, that's a פסוק pasuk in משלי. Mishlei. But
בן סירא אומר Ben Sira omer אף לילות, af leilot, even the
nights are bad for a poor person. Don't think you go to
sleep and now, oh, poor and rich, it's all the same, once
they are asleep, they're unconscious. Nope, not true. Okay? So here's בן
סירא Ben Sira helps clarify, and it's something worthy of דרשני. darsheni.
בשפל גגים גגו, bishfal gagim gago, his roof is lower than everybody
else's roof, so everybody's rain, you know, from their roof goes on
to his roof, so he doesn't even get to sleep well at
night. Okay? ובמרום הרים כרמו, ubimarom harim karmo, and his mountain, his
vineyard is at the top of the mountain, not below where the
soil is good. And what's the result of that? ממטר גגים לגגו,
mimatar gagim legago, so everybody else's rain winds up coming onto his
roof. Okay? ומעפר כרמו לכרמים, ume'afar karmo lecharamim, and the opposite, his
you know when he's doing his planting his vineyard up there, all
the good soil rolls down into everybody else's soil. Okay, so that's
not exactly the nights being bad, but anyway. Okay, so now we
move on. אמר רבי זירא אמר רב. amar Rabbi Zeira amar Rav.
You can't sleep at night because of all the rain.
Well, that's the first part. The first part is the night. The
vineyard I meant. אמר רבי זירא אמר רב. amar Rabbi Zeira amar
Rav. מאי דכתיב, mai dechtiv, what's meant by the verse כל ימי
עני רעים? kol yemei ani ra'im? So now we are going to
just talk about like who's got it bad in this world and
who's got it good, okay, and not necessarily saying that it's deserved
or well, we'll see. Okay. What does it mean all the days
of the poor person are bad? So אלו בעלי תלמוד, elu ba'alei
Talmud, people who learn גמרא, Gemara, 'cause you know, you have to
anguish so much. It's hard. Like, you know, you've got to stretch
your brain, and it's not always clear, and it's so, you know,
the learning is difficult. Okay. וטוב לב משתה תמיד. vetov lev mishteh
tamid. The end of the verse here in משלי, Mishlei, because before
we just quoted the beginning, כל ימי עני רעים, kol yemei ani
ra'im, but the end of the verse says וטוב לב משתה תמיד.
vetov lev mishteh tamid. You know, and the one of like, you
know, and a good heart, you know, is always like a feast.
Okay, so are you supposed to always be in a feast? Right,
it's like a good question, right? Are you supposed, maybe it doesn't
necessarily mean it's the right choice just because you're happier most of
the time. You might be happy because you're oblivious and you're not
engaging in serious issues. So that's, so that's a little bit of
that subtext I'm hearing. The first part of the verse is not
necessarily the wrong decision. It just means that things are tough. Okay,
so yes, learning גמרא Gemara makes things tough. But if you want
to just have a good time, אלו בעלי משנה. elu ba'alei Mishnah.
You know, read משנה. Mishnah. משנה's Mishnah nice and easy. It's in
simple Hebrew. It's simple apodictic statements. You'll have a ball, you'll have
a blast. Okay? So I don't know if that's better, but you
know, it's always easier to read a junk novel or go see,
you know, than to read serious literature. Okay, does that mean it's
the right choice? That's a different question. Yes, you wanted to say
something, מיכאל?
Michael? One of the things I listen to is like משנה Mishnah
has an answer, and גמרא Gemara many times is just a...
Oh, not having an answer. That's true. Okay, that's a good point.
But now we're going to...
Okay.
רבא אמר איפכא. Rava amar ipcha. Now רבא Rava says no, no,
no, because you have to think not about just the process, but
like sort of, you know, what results from it or whatever. You
have to think bigger picture.
רבא אמר איפכא. Rava amar ipcha. Because, you know, yes, גמרא Gemara
learning is hard, but it's more deeply satisfying. You know, learning משנה
Mishnah is easy, but it's like empty calories. So junk food is
great, but it's empty calories, right? So you know, so which one
do you think is better or not? Okay. והיינו דאמרי רב משראשיא
משמיה דרבא. vehainu de'amrei Rav Mesharshiya mishmeih deRava. מאי דכתיב, mai dechtiv,
what's meant by the verse מסיע אבנים יעצב בהם? masi'a avanim ye'atzev
bahem? The one who sort of has to move stones is anguished
by it. I mean, that's real hard work. Imagine trying to schlepp
like huge boulders or whatever. יעצב
בהם. ye'atzev bahem. אלו בעלי משנה. elu ba'alei Mishnah. These are the
people of the משנה Mishnah because, you know, one way of understanding
why you know is is that you're... okay, so again, it's not
the hard work, but actually but like it's in the end you
like you carry this big burden because it's just learning a lot
of facts, right? So thinking about like you know something to carry,
it's a big heavy thing. It's just like knowing a lot of
facts, and in the end it's disappointing. What do you have from
it? You don't really have a deep understanding. Okay. ובוקע עצים יסכן
בהם. ubokei'a etzim yisachen bahem. But if you chop wood, you get...
you warm yourself with it. You know, it's very vigorous activity.
Doesn't it mean like סכנה? sakanah?
No, well that's the way גמרא's Gemara reading it, and רשי's Rashi
reading it anyway. It means from סכנות sachanot or whatever or something
to provide warmth. Apparently if you're schlepping big stones, you're also sweating
and you know warming yourself. But okay, I mean I don't know,
maybe the friction with the wood. Anyway, but somehow, so this you
know, this is good, vigorous, outdoor, healthy activity. So, and the chopping
of the wood, you understand, right? The learning of the משנה Mishnah
is just memorizing facts. The chopping of the wood is like analyzing,
getting to the depth, breaking it up into its component parts, right?
And
ultimately... אלו בעלי תלמוד Elu baalei Talmud excuse me yes.
So there are מסכתות masechtos of משנה mishnah that don't have גמרא.
gemara.
That is true. It's not only a question about priorities, okay? Yeah,
obviously you have to learn משנה, mishnah, yeah, yeah.
So again, what do we know of this? It's important who says
what. רב ששת Rav Sheshet is in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and
so he puts... Oh!
Oh,
thank you! Oh, שכוח, shkoach, I didn't notice that. Okay. All right,
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and בבל, Bavel, right, because ארץ... All right,
thank you very much. Good, good insight, yes.
Also, a stone is inanimate, and a tree is like a living,
growing...
Oh, that's nice! So the משנה mishnah is like a fixed text,
whereas גמרא gemara is constantly expanding. Good going guys! All right, okay.
I'll be absent more. Okay, so anyway, so okay, רבי חנינא Rabbi
Chanina אומר, omer, כל ימי עני רעים, kol yemei ani raim, זה
מי שיש לו אשה רעה, ze mi sheyesh lo ishah raah, back
to wives, okay? So this is a... so all of a poor
person is a man who has a bad wife, okay, so וטוב
לב משתה תמיד זה שיש לו אשה טובה, vetov lev mishteh tamid
ze sheyesh lo ishah tovah, a good wife. All right, that's not
as I think interesting as the earlier points.
רבי ינאי Rabbi Yannai אומר, omer, כל ימי עני רעים, kol yemei
ani raim, זה איסטניס. ze istanis. This is somebody that is like
fastidious, okay? So like, you know, has germs and every... you know,
he's got to eat in a certain way and it's always a
question about the environment around him, you know, the air, the... you
know, the air, you know, whatever, you know, the pollen count or
whatever. You know, that type of person is always
in anguish, okay?
וטוב לב משתה תמיד זה שדעתו יפה, vetov lev mishteh tamid ze
shedaato yafah, יפה. yafah. So it basically means like it's all cool,
it's all fine, it's all gold. So... so it's sometimes, you know,
you might think that means refined, but like actually there's a משנה
Mishnah sometimes that talks about like things that are somewhat disgusting to
eat and it says נפש היפה תאכלנה. nefesh hayafah tochalena. So which
basically means like somebody who's like cool with anything, I don't know,
that's my... that's my
contemporary idiom. But somebody who's like, "It's all fine, you know, whatever,"
they have a very wide experience thing. You just want to say
something, מיכאל? Michal? Okay. So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan אומר, omer, כל
ימי עני רעים, kol yemei ani raim, זה רחמני. ze rachmani. Somebody
who is, you know, not just sympathetic or... you know, empathetic, but
also somebody who is highly sensitive. Everything they... they feel deeply about
everything, right? So they're always feeling other people's pain and they don't
have any boundaries, right? So they're constantly suffering the suffering of the
world. Okay? וטוב לב משתה תמיד זה אכזרי. vetov lev mishteh tamid
ze achzari. If you've totally got a hard heart, you never let
anything bother you, you know, fine. So you know, he's like the
easiest people... people have it easiest in this world are the people
without a conscience, you know, you go around, nothing ever... you know,
nothing ever bothers you, so you know, you're not feeling other people's
pain. Not necessarily a good thing, but it's describing a reality. Okay?
אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי Amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi אומר, omer,
כל ימי עני רעים, kol yemei ani raim, זה שדעתו קצרה. ze
shedaato ktzarah. So what's קצרה ktzarah as opposed to before we had
איסטניס? istanis? Or actually קצרה ktzarah is מכניס ללבו כל דאגות חבירו
ודואג כל מה שעתיד לבוא אליו. machnis lelibo kol daagot chaveiro vedoeg
kol mah sheatid lavo eilav. So this is somebody that also like
borrows other people's anxieties. So I guess anxieties is different than, you
know, being overly empathetic, right? Anxieties is like... you know, it's sort
of like the same before about the... where did we have it
before? About worrying tomorrow's worries, right? So you're just worrying about everything.
How do you get דעתו קצרה? daato ktzarah? I don't... well, I
don't know. It's like you don't have... it's not... it's not easy
for you to... to... to handle stuff. רש"י Rashi has another explanation
which is רגזן, ragzan, somebody who doesn't have patience and very easily
gets angry and upset about things. That fits a little bit more
I think the image of דעתו קצרה. daato ktzarah. וטוב לב משתה
תמיד זה שדעתו רחבה, vetov lev mishteh tamid ze shedaato rechavah, which
would be the opposite. Either you don't... you don't have all these
anxieties or you don't let... you don't react like to things and
let them anger you. Okay? ואמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, Vaamar Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi, כל ימי עני רעים, kol yemei ani raim, והאיכא
שבתות וימים טובים? vehaika shabbatos veyamim tovim? What do you mean all
the days? Like on שבת Shabbos everybody at least gets to, you
know, have a day where you know, where they get to dress
up and have nice food and even רש"י Rashi says even a
poor person makes sure that they have good food on שבת, Shabbos,
that's the whole point of שבת. Shabbos. There was... somebody was just
showing me a few weeks ago a beautiful thing that there's actually
a video of the רב Rav in one of his יארצייט yahrzeit
lectures. I didn't know it even existed, apparently you can find it
on YouTube. And he's talking about, you know, about like how שבת
Shabbos transforms people and there's this beautiful thing where he talks about
like this person who he was like...
you know, I don't know, some like a porter, a שלעפער, shlepper,
you know, and he always looked... whatever, he always looked disheveled, whatever
way you saw him, he would help people, you know, bring their
stuff from the dock. Anyway, and then on שבת, Shabbos, this person
comes up to him and he's like, you know, in a בעקיטשע,
bekishe, whatever, looks... and he says, "You don't recognize me? I'm יוסף
Yosef the porter." You know, and he was talking about how like...
how...
whatever, it was just a beaut... I can't do it justice. It
was just beautiful about like, you know, the people that during the
rest of the week are like the שלעפערס shleppers and the this
and the that, on שבת Shabbos everybody becomes like, you know, בני
מלכים, benei melachim, everybody becomes regal. So הגמרא hagmarah says,
"What do you mean כל ימי עני רעים? kol yemei ani raim?
והאיכא שבתות וימים טובים?" vehaika shabbatos veyamim tovim? כי דשמואל, ki deShmuel,
like שמואל. Shmuel. Yeah,
but you know here talking specifically about the food, you eat nicer
food on שבת. Shabbos. That might be, but changing your normal pattern
also is the beginning of starting to get sick. So if on
שבת Shabbos you have nice food that you don't have during the
rest of the week, that's also not only something good, it might
give you a stomach ache by Sunday or something. Okay, yes, Charlie.
שמואל Shmuel was a doctor.
Oh, that's true too. All right, everybody's bringing in biographies here, great.
Okay, so תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. Back to שיר השירים. Shir HaShirim.
So, not שיר השירים, Shir HaShirim, back to things you're supposed to
read or not read. Don't read the apocrypha or maybe don't read
them in a certain way. Don't read בן סירא Ben Sira maybe
or don't read it in a certain way. Okay, and now we
get to reading actually תנ"ך, Tanakh, but reading it in a wrong
way. We're not going to say he אין לו חלק לעולם הבא,
ein lo chelek l'olam haba, but that actually does not sort of
respect itself, that it's like the flip. The other's the problem we're
giving it elevated status as if it were scripture, and here we're
going to deal with scripture and giving it treating it in ways
that's not appropriate for scripture. Okay? תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. הקורא פסוק
של שיר השירים ועשאו כמין זמר. hakore pasuk shel Shir HaShirim v'asao
k'min zemer. You read a פסוק pasuk in שיר השירים Shir HaShirim
and you make it into a nice song. Okay? והקורא פסוק
בבית המשתאות בלא זמנו.
v'hakore pasuk b'veit
hamishta'ot b'lo zmano. You read some other verse in the in the
drinking house בלא זמנו. b'lo zmano. What does it mean like not
in its time? That's a funny phrase, but the point is that
your ways right, not in the right context. That the context is
you can't exactly quantify it, but you know because what do you
mean? We sing you know, we put פסוקים psukim to music. Okay,
fine. There's an idea of doing
it כדי שתהא
גמרא זמר בכל יום זמר בכל יום.
k'dei
she-tehe Gemara
zemer bechol yom zemer bechol yom. Right, exactly, there you go. Right
before we actually set about turning your גמרא Gemara into זמר. zemer.
So there's a way you do it in a proper context and
there's a way you do it that you turn it into just
like some you know like like like like what? A bar song?
Thank you, exactly. Okay, so מביא רעה לעולם mevi ra'ah l'olam brings
evil to the world. מפני שהתורה חוגרת שק, mipnei she-haTorah chogeret sak,
that's a great image here. The תורה Torah puts itself in a
sackcloth. You have actually somehow like you know like you you've impacted
the very nature I like the personification of תורה Torah and being
like stripped from its glory, you know, is like a great personification
here. It puts on a sackcloth ועומדת לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא v'omedet
lifnei HaKadosh Baruch Hu and stands before God ואומרת לפניו v'omeret lefanav
ריבונו של עולם, Ribono shel Olam, Master of the universe, עשוני בניך
ככינור שמנגנים בו לצים. asuni banecha ke-chinnor she-menagnim bo leitzim. Your kids
have made me like a flute that like you know like I
don't know like bums are you know spending their time on, like
that's what I am, I'm some harmonica? Okay, you know that's what
I've become. So אמר לה, amar lah, בתי, biti, my daughter, בשעה
שאוכלים ושותים במה יעסקו. besha'ah she-ochlim v'shotim bameh ya'asoku. This is so
fascinating. God here is now defending you know us. Right, what do
you want them to do? They're eating and drinking, at least they're
learning תורה. Torah. It's almost like the story about the חסיד Chassid
and the מתנגד, Misnaged, right? Sees a guy on the side of
the road changing his tire and he's you know and he's דאווענינג
davening מנחה Mincha you know as he's changing his tire. So the
מתנגד Misnaged says ach, how look at they're mistreating like the דאווענינג,
davening, his hands are filthy oily and he he thinks he's praying
to God like this. And the חסיד Chassid said ריבונו של עולם,
Ribono shel Olam, Your children even when their hands are filthy with
grease they're thinking about You and praying to You, right? So that's
the debate here between God so God is trying to console the
תורה. Torah. What do you want them to do? They're eating and
drinking, at least they're they're singing תורה, Torah, it's better than singing
some pop
song. So במה יעסקו. bameh ya'asoku. אמרה לפניו, amrah lefanav, the תורה
Torah says, ריבונו של עולם, Ribono shel Olam, excuse me Master of
the universe, אם בעלי מקרא הן יעסקו בתורה ובנביאים ובכתובים. im ba'alei
mikra hen ya'asoku baTorah u'viNevi'im u'viKhtuvim. אם בעלי משנה הן יעסקו במשנה
ובהלכות ובאגדות. im ba'alei Mishnah hen ya'asoku baMishnah u've-halakhot u've-aggadot. You know
what? There's things that they could discuss. They could discuss תנ"ך, Tanakh,
they could discuss you know מדרשים. Midrashim. ואם בעלי תלמוד הן יעסקו
בהלכות פסח בפסח
ובהלכות עצרת בעצרת ובהלכות חג בחג. v'im ba'alei Talmud hen ya'asoku b'hilkhot
Pesach b'Pesach u'v'hilkhot Atzeret b'Atzeret u'v'hilkhot chag be-chag. It's interesting the link
of בעלי תלמוד ba'alei Talmud with הלכה. halakha. Why not learn גמרא?
Gemara? בהלכות חג בחג. b'hilkhot chag be-chag. Now what type of an
answer is that? The answer is you know he like he said
they could be talking about פסוקים. psukim. Yeah, talking about פסוקים, psukim,
not singing them. Okay, fine. You're sitting you're having a good time,
say a דבר תורה. d'var Torah. Nobody says it has to be
the table have to be like the בית מדרש. Beis Medrash. The
דבר תורה d'var Torah you say at the table is not the
same type of a learning you do at the בית מדרש. Beis
Medrash. Okay? Okay, fine, so schmooze in learning you know. And now
of course it's a little bit bothers me the whole discussion of
הלכה, halakha, like you're not supposed to teach הלכה halakha when you're
a little drunk, you're eating and drinking or whatever. But again presumably
it means like schmoozing in it. There's things you can talk about
that's a lighter form of treating the and still treats the תורה
Torah with respect rather than turning the תורה Torah into some type
of a pop song which is what the sort of the image
here. Yeah Charlie.
Yeah, but much of תנ"ך Tanakh was meant was originally written to
be sung.
Yeah, in the right context. Nobody the problem is not the singing,
the problem is singing it as a pop song, you know, singing
it as some type of a as a bar song.
Maybe מניח להם. m'niach lahem.
Oh, so that's why the גמרא Gemara doesn't quantify it. What is
זמנו? zmano? You know context matters.
Well, I'm looking at רש"י Rashi who
says הקורא שיר השירים ועשאו כמין זמר, hakore Shir HaShirim v'asao k'min
zemer, it says הקורא בבית המשתאות hakore b'veit hamishta'ot you know. not
been the practice of כל ישראל. Klal Yisrael. Okay,
רבי שמעון בן אלעזר בשם רבי שמעון בן חנניא, Rabbi Shimon ben
Elazar beshem Rabbi Shimon ben Chananya, כל הקורא פסוק בזמנו, kol hakoreh
pasuk bizmano, if you read it in the right time, in the
right context presumably etc., maybe טובה לעולם. tovah le'olam. That's the flip
side. שנאמר ודבר בעתו מה טוב. Shene'emar vidavar be'ito mah tov. How
good is it to do it in the right way, you know?
So it's not a problem intrinsically, you know, and maybe even singing
isn't a problem, the point is what's the context. Okay, now moving
on to the things that אין לו חלק, ein lo chelek, והלוחש
על המכה. vehalochesh al hamakah. Obviously we seem to be a wide
range of things here from fundamental principles of faith, you know, to
dangerous activity about reading certain types of things as scripture, to I
don't know, making an incantation over a wound, which seems to which
was usually pretty common and it's not exactly clear like why is
that wrong like even if we think like I don't know it's
a stupid superstition is it an עבירה? aveirah? Even if it's an
עבירה, aveirah, why is אין לו חלק לעולם הבא, ein lo chelek
le'olam haba, הבא, haba, you know? So let's take a look. Okay,
כל המחלה אשר שמתי במצרים לא אשים עליך Kol hamachalah asher samti
beMitzrayim lo asim alecha was the was the example the משנה mishna
gave. אמר רבי יוחנן וברוקק בה. Amar Rabbi Yochanan uverokek bah. Only
if you spit and then recite it because then you're like saying
a פסוק pasuk or saying God's name over spit. And that's disrespectful
to God's name. Even if that's true, אין לו חלק לעולם הבא,
ein lo chelek le'olam haba, really? Like there's not other things you
want to put on that list before that? You know, so so
one really wonders, you know, what is the meaning at this stage
about being on this list. Is the meaning about being on this
list like things we disapprove of but that we can't actually say
are halachically forbidden? Okay, fine, but then why what does it do
to have that on the same list as אומר אין תורה מן
השמים ואין תחיית המתים מן התורה? omer ein Torah min hashamayim ve'ein
techiyat hametim min haTorah? You know, it's a little bit like undermining
the weight of the beginning of the list. I really don't know
how to fully explain that. It's, you know, but anyway. איתמר, Itmar,
it said, רבא אמר אפילו נגד צרעת, Rava amar afilu neged tzara'at,
even if somebody says the פסוק נגע צרעת כי תהיה, pasuk nega
tzara'at ki tihyeh, what's the פסוק pasuk רש״י Rashi quotes? נגע צרעת
כי תהיה באדם והובא אל
הכהן. Nega tzara'at ki tihyeh ba'adam vehuva el hakohen.
So you're saying that over some מכה. makah. Why would I think
that's different? Because it doesn't have God's name. So maybe it's less
problematic because it doesn't have God's name. No, it's still problematic. Okay.
רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina says אפילו ויקרא אל משה. afilu Vayikra el
Moshe. Now that does have God's name, וידבר ה׳ אליו מאהל מועד
לאמר, Vayedaber Hashem elav me'ohel moed lemor, but you might think, well,
since that doesn't have a whole magical incantation context, like because you're
not sort of it's not directly relevant to the wound, maybe it's
less problematic. No, it's
still problematic. You're still saying it over the wound, you're still spitting
it and so on. Okay. תנו רבנן סכין וממשמשים בבני מעיים בשבת.
Tanu rabanan sachin umemashmeshim bivnei me'ayim beShabbat. So with this you're the
this is a שבת Shabbat discussion, but we'll see how it's relevant.
You can put oil and like, you know, if somebody has an
upset stomach, you can like rub oil and rub it into like
the stomach, you know, like on that part of the body on
שבת Shabbat because even and it's not considered a רפואה. refuah. Since
people would normally put oil on their skin on שבת, Shabbat, even
though you're doing this because somebody has an upset stomach, it's not
obviously רפואה. refuah. Therefore it's
permitted. ולוחשים לחישת נחשים ועקרבים בשבת. Velochashim lechishat nechashim ve'akrabim beShabbat. This
is why we brought it in because of the לחישה. lechishah. You
can say certain types of incantations that'll stop the snakes and scorpions
from biting. Okay, and it's not like trapping on שבת, Shabbat, you
know, because it's just an incantation, you're not physically trapping them.
Okay.
ומעבירים כלי על גבי העין בשבת. Uma'avirin kli al gabei ha'ayin beShabbat.
Eye problems, apparently I was reading this somewhere I was trying to
remember where I was reading this, but there like it was a
very, very large eye problems in the ancient world because of like
of like, you know, you would put whatever your hands would be
dirty and, you know, infections or whatever was a major it was
a major source of medical issues. Anyway, so one of the things
you do is like you put like a cold metal thing on
top of an eye like if it's inflamed, right, and that helps
like cool it down. So you're allowed to do that on שבת,
Shabbat, which is interesting that that's not considered to be a רפואה.
refuah. אמר רבן שמעון בן גמליאל במה דברים אמורים בכלי הניטל. Amar
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel bamah devarim amurim bekhli hanital. That's only if
it's a it's a type of a vessel that you're allowed to
move. It's not מוקצה. muktzah. אבל בכלי שאינו ניטל, Aval bekhli she'eino
nital, if it's מוקצה, muktzah,
אסור. asur. You're
not allowed to. Okay.
ואין שואלים בדבר שדים בשבת. Ve'ein sho'alin bidvar shedim beShabbat. You're not
allowed to inquire of the of the שדים shedim on שבת. Shabbat.
You know, apparently you can do it the rest of the week.
Okay, but but we'll see the next line. And רש״י Rashi says
why would you ask the שדים? shedim? You would ask them about,
hey, do you know where I lost my keys? And the שדים
shedim might answer you. And the reason you're not allowed to do
it on שבת Shabbat is because it's דובר דבר, dover davar, because
it's weekday activity. I really am not going to expand upon this
because I don't know what to say. Anyway, so okay. רבי יוסי
אומר אף בחול אסור. Rabbi Yossi omer af bechol asur. So you're
not even supposed to ask from שדים shedim even during the weekday.
How do you know why? What's the איסור? issur? You're not doing
magic, whatever, you're just asking the שדים. shedim. Okay, anyway, so. אף
בכל אסור. af b'chol assur. And presumably רש"י Rashi says not because
of an איסור issur but because of סכנה. sakana. Once you start
getting into conversations with שדים, sheidim, you might make yourself you know
exposed, you know vulnerable to that. So, אמר רב הונא Amar Rav
Huna for now of course there's a question: הלכה כרבי יוסי halacha
k'Rebbi Yose or אין הלכה כרבי יוסי? ein halacha k'Rebbi Yose? Question
of the גרסא. girsa. I really need to know because I want
to ask the שד sheid because I still can't find the keys
I lost here a month ago. I'm telling you, I had to
get a whole new set of keys made, it was not fun.
Anyways, אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, ואמר רב יוסף, v'amar Rav
Yosef, ואמרי לה v'amri lah רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, לא אמר אלא
משום סכנה. lo amar ella mishum sakana. Even רבי יוסי, Rebbi Yose,
he wasn't of an איסור issur concern, it was a סכנה sakana
concern.
כי הא דרבי יצחק בר יוסף, ki ha d'Rebbi Yitzchak bar Yosef,
דאבלע בארזא. d'ivla b'arza. רבי יצחק בר יוסף Rebbi Yitzchak bar Yosef
apparently was being chased by a שד sheid or maybe got into,
and anyway, he somehow was swallowed up by a cedar tree. ואיעביד
ליה ניסא ופקע ארזא ופלטיה. v'isavid leh nissa u'paka arza u'paltay. And
that is, and maybe he would have died even or whatever, but
some miracle happened and the cedar tree burst open and therefore he
got saved. I don't know the whole story. Anyway, moving on. Don't
get involved with שדים. sheidim. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, סכין וממשמשין sachin
u'm'mashmishin back to this issue, now we're digressing a little, back to
this issue of putting oil on your skin even for your stomach
or whatever. סכין וממשמשין בבני מעיים בשבת sachin u'm'mashmishin bivnei me'ayim b'Shabbos
ובלבד שלא יעשה כדרך שהוא עושה בחול. u'vilvad shelo ya'aseh k'derech she'hu
oseh b'chol. Do it with a שינוי. shinui. Okay, yes, it's true,
it's not totally looks like רפואה. refuah. The basic rule is you're
allowed to do things for health purposes if it's not obviously רפואה.
refuah. You got sore gums, you're allowed to like, you know, drink
like some schnapps or something if it helps numb the pain in
the gums, but don't like swosh it around on your gums, that'll
be obvious. Okay, so you can put oil on your skin, that
was a normal thing done, and maybe even like rub it in,
okay, and that's considered not a רפואה. refuah. But he says, but
you know what? You should do it with a שינוי shinui because
it might start looking a little bit
too much like it.
Right, exactly. Okay, so what's, what's doing it with a, not doing
it the normal way? היכי עביד? Heichi avid? רב חמא בר חנינא
Rav Chama bar Chanina אמר amar סך ואחר כך ממשמש. sach v'achar
kach m'mashmesh. Don't start by rubbing and then add the oil. First
add the oil and then rub, which is a normal thing you
would do if it wasn't for a health purpose. רבי יוחנן Rebbi
Yochanan אומר omer סך וממשמש בבת אחת. sach u'm'mashmesh b'vas achas. You
sort of like can be putting on the oil as you're rubbing,
but again, but don't first begin the rubbing and then add the
oil, then it's obvious that it's not about the oil. Right, exactly.
Okay, so it's not a מלאכה, melacha, it's just a רפואה refuah
concern. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan.
שרי שמן ושרי ביצים. sarei shemen v'sarei beitzim. So the, excuse me,
שרי, sarei, excuse me, שרי שמן ושרי ביצים, sarei shemen v'sarei beitzim,
the, the angels that are the officers over oil and of eggs,
מותרין לשאול בהם. mutarin lishol bahem. Those you're allowed to inquire of
them. So, I don't know what it's talking about. רש"י Rashi says
יש מעשה שדים ששואלים על ידי שמן. yeish ma'aseh sheidim she'shoalin al
yedei shemen. So actually, so it's not the, excuse me, it's not
the שדים sheidim that are in charge of oil and eggs, but
the שדים sheidim who somehow can be invoked through doing, through doing
things with oil and with eggs. Okay, I don't really know what
we're talking about. Okay, move on. Like we're learning the beginning of
ברכות. Brachos. Okay, מותרין לשאול בהן. mutarin lishol bahen. אלא Ella מפני
שמכזבין. mipnei she'mechazvin. But be careful, because they're, they
lie. Okay, so you're not always, they'll tell you something, it'll be
maybe a half-truth or whatever. לוחשין על שמן שבכלי ואין לוחשין על
שמן שביד. lochshin al shemen she'bakli v'ein lochshin al shemen she'b'yad. Now
back to לחישה lechisha concerns, and again, I don't know if this
is because of in order to invoke, רש"י Rashi says it's in
order to invoke the שדים. sheidim. You're allowed to, that לחישה, lechisha,
when people do these incantations to invoke שדים, sheidim, they do it
on oil that's in a vessel, but they don't do it, this
is the way רש"י Rashi is reading this, it's not telling you
it's permitted, it's descriptive, but they don't do it over oil that
is in the hand. And that's important for you to know, because
if somebody whispered some שדים-based sheidim incantation over oil, that oil might
actually be injurious to you. So, you know, so let's see the
consequence of knowing that they do it on oil that's in the
vessel, not oil in the hand. לפיכך L'fichach סכין משמן שביד, sachin
mishemen she'b'yad, you can go ahead and have somebody put, you know,
oil on you from oil that's coming from the hand, ואין סכין
משמן שבכלי, v'ein sachin mishemen she'bakli, but if it's coming out of
the vessel and you saw them doing something that looked suspicious or
you have a reason to suspect them, you might want to be
concerned because maybe there were some injurious incantations measured over there.
I don't understand why this is not in the rubric of לא
תנחשו, lo tenachashu, it sounds like this is...
I understand, yeah, I understand. You have to figure out exactly the
parameters of that. But yes. רבי יצחק בר, Rebbi Yitzchak bar, I
understand, yes, there's all these magics that are אסור assur and all
this other stuff that's not מעשה, ma'aseh, not דרכי האמורי, darchei ha'Emori,
not considered אסור. assur. Look, even the לא תנחשו, lo tenachashu, right,
the גמרא Gemara also talks about what's a סימנא טבא simana tava
and not a good sign of future things. So exactly figuring out
the line is very complicated. Okay, רבי יצחק בר שמואל בר מרתא
Rebbi Yitzchak bar Shmuel bar Marta איקלע, ikla, now we're going to
have a story that supports this idea. איקלע לההוא אושפיזא, ikla l'hahu
ushpiza, he came to a certain inn. אייתו ליה משחא במנא, aisu
leh mishcha b'mana, and they brought him oil in a vessel. Bad,
bad job. You should have said, I first want you to pour
it into your hand or something, I don't know. Anyway, of course
I don't know, once the incantation was in the vessel, does it
help to put it in the hand? Presumably not. Because what did
he do anyway? שף, shaf, he rubbed it on himself, and presumably
on his face. ונפקן ליה צימחי באפיה, v'nafkan leh tzimchi b'apei, and
all these blisters or... boils appeared on his face. Okay, נפק לשוק
nafak leshuk he went out to the marketplace, חזיתיה ההיא איתתא chaziteih
hahi iteta and a certain woman saw him, אמרה amra זיקא דחמת
כחזינא zika decheimat kachazina I see here the wind, the spirit of
חמת, Cheimat, which is apparently was a certain shade. Okay, הכא. hacha.
עבד לה מילתא avad lah milta
so she did some some some neutralizing incantation or some type of
of a ritual or something, עבד לה מילתא avad lah milta and
he was healed. Fine. Moving on. אמר ליה רב אבא לרבא לרבא
בר מרי amar lei Rav Abba le-Rabba le-Rabba bar Mari כתיב ketiv
it says כל המחלה אשר שמתי במצרים לא אשים עליך כי אני
ה' רופאך kol hamachala asher samti be-Mitzrayim lo asim alecha ki ani
Hashem rofecha that was the פסוק pasuk that the משנה gave as
the example of the incantation, I will not give you any of
the illness of Egypt because I am God who heals you. דכי
מאחר דלא שם רפואה למה? de-ki me-acher de-lo sam refua lama?
If you're not going to make me sick in the first place,
לא אשים עליך lo asim alecha why do I need to be
healed? Okay, so אמר ליה amar lei הכי אמר רבי יוחנן hachi
amar Rabbi Yochanan מקרא זה מעצמו נדרש. mikra zeh me-atzmo nidrash. You
can sort of get the meaning of it just by from it
unpack the verse itself. שנאמר shene'emar ויאמר אם שמוע תשמע לקול ה'
אלהיך vayomer im shamoa tishma le-kol Hashem Elokecha then כל המחלה אשר
שמתי. kol hamachala asher samti.
If you listen to my voice, I won't put this up. So
there's two parts to this verse. So אם תשמע לא
אשים. im tishma lo asim. אם שמוע תשמע im shamoa tishma
then you won't get sick in the first place. ואם לא תשמע
ve-im lo tishma but even if you don't listen, then אשים asim
I if you don't listen you're assuming אשים asim I will make
you sick. אע"פ כן כי אני ה' רופאך af al pi chen
ki ani Hashem rofecha but even if you get sick, always know
that I'm here to I will heal I'm avail- you know I'm
God who can heal you, you can pray, you can whatever. So
even if you get sick, even if you're not safe from the
illness, I still remain your healer. אמר רבה בר בר חנה amar
Rabba bar bar Chana כשחלה רבי אליעזר. ke-she-chala Rabbi Eliezer. Now, because
we're talking about illness or whatever, anyway, we get these great there
are so many of these deathbed stories with רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer,
right we had one right if you remember, right from in בבא
מציעא Bava Metzia we had one was it בבא- Bava- no, that
was just בבא מציעא. Bava Metzia.
Oh, right, it was in, yeah, it was earlier in סנהדרין, Sanhedrin,
right, right. Yeah. So anyway, yeah, oh no, the בבא מציעא Bava
Metzia is the earlier story about the תנור של עכנאי. Tanur shel
Achnai. Anyway, so here's another deathbed story with all the great rabbis
coming and he had been in חרם cherem prior to this if
you remember. Anyway, כשחלה רבי אליעזר ke-she-chala Rabbi Eliezer נכנסו תלמידיו לבקרו.
nichnasu talmidav le-vakro. So his students came to visit him. אמר להם
amar lahem חמה עזה יש בעולם. chama azah yesh ba-olam.
There's a strong sun in the world. So what does that mean?
So רש"י Rashi says that it means על עצמו שכעס עליו המקום
והושיבו בחיים. al atzmo she-ka'as alav ha-Makom ve-hoshivo ba-chayim. Right, exactly, like
I'm feeling really I'm burning up, okay, exactly. התחילו הן בוכין hitchilu
hen bochin and they started crying and classically ורבי עקיבא משחק. ve-Rabbi
Akiva meshachek. Rabbi Akiva was laughing. Okay. אמרו לו amru lo למה
אתה משחק? lama ata meshachek? Why are you laughing? I'm telling you
that I'm burning up with a high fever. אמר להם amar lahem
or they said the the other students, the רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva's
colleagues, אמר להם amar lahem he said to them, ואתם למה אתם
בוכים? ve-atem lama atem bochin? Why are you crying? Like it's a
classic trope, right? אמרו לו amru lo they said to him, אפשר
ספר תורה שרוי בצער efshar sefer torah sharui be-tza'ar again, רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer is compared to a ספר תורה, sefer torah, and that
was in the other stories as well, at the time we mentioned
the fact that right, he was not so much into sort of
being creative and sort of darshaning תורה Torah on his own, he
was more about just passing down everything he had received. So it's
almost got like he's full with everything but it's static, you know,
so it's not the מעיין המתגבר. Ma'ayan Ha-mitgaber. So anyway, he's a
ספר תורה. sefer torah. So if the ספר תורה sefer torah is
there in an anguish and pain with a fever, ולא נבכה? ve-lo
nivkeh? how could we not cry? We're feeling for him. אמר להם
amar lahem לכך אני משחק. le-kach ani meshachek. That's why I'm happy,
I'm laughing. כל זמן שאני רואה רבי שאין יינו מחמיץ kol zman
she-ani ro'eh rabbi she-ein yeino machmitz as long as I see my
rabbi that everything is going good for him, his wine doesn't spoil,
ואין פשתנו לוקה ve-ein pishtano lokeh his flax isn't is in is
in good shape, ואין שמנו מבאיש ve-ein shamno mav'ish his oil's not
getting spoiled, ואין דבשנו מדביש ve-ein dvashno madvish his honey isn't congealed
or whatever, אמרתי שמא חס ושלום קיבל רבי עולמו? amarti shema chas
ve-shalom kibel rabbi olamo? I was concerned that maybe he's received all
his reward in this world. ועכשיו שאני רואה רבי בצער ve-achshav she-ani
ro'eh rabbi be-tza'ar now I see that he's in anguish, so אני
שמח. ani same'ach. Oh good, he'll he'll
he'll suffer in this world so he'll be rewarded in the world
to come, which is quite fast- ironic in multiple ways. First of
all, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer was in חרם cherem and he was
cut off from his colleagues. So what? So he hasn't suffered as
a result of because he might be materially well off that means
that he's not like שרוי בצער sharui be-tza'ar and so on? And
number two, it's also ironic because רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva of course,
you know, had his terrible end, right? So I mean maybe that's
not ironic, but like it's a little bit okay, you think it's
good to suffer in this world like okay. Anyway, so anyway, this
caught רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer's attention. Now, one of the things that
עקיבא Akiva might have been doing, right, this might have been I
mean I'm not necessarily advising this strategy but this might have been
and we see this in the next story intentionally sort of with
a pastoral sensitivity. Like you know if somebody is basically, you know,
crying and everybody's crying with him it doesn't necessarily like they say
like misery loves company but also it means if I'm miserable I
want you to be miserable too. Right? If all you're doing is
say oh I feel so terrible for you it doesn't necessarily make
me feel better. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is saying like oh this
is a good thing, you know, you're suffering in this world so
you'll get reward in the world to come. So I'm not saying
it'll necessarily work, but at least it has an option of making
him giving him a reframing right that made him actually feel like...
maybe I should have a different way of looking at this and
feeling a little bit better about it. Okay.
So but let's see what his response was. אמר לו עקיבא כלום
חסרתי מן התורה כולה? Amar lo Akiva klum chisarti min haTorah kulah?
What, Akiva, you think that somehow I sell short? I deserve to
be punished in this world? What did I ever do that was
wrong?
So they still don't realize the reason why he's in חרם. cherem.
Well, that's true also. But also the language of חסרתי מן התורה,
chisarti min haTorah, right? For him, it's all about having all of
it or not having all of it. It's like the quantity of
information, right? You know, it's so anyway, but אמר לו, amar lo,
he said
to him, למדתנו רבנו כי אדם אין צדיק בארץ אשר יעשה טוב
ולא יחטא. limdatenu rabenu ki adam ein tzaddik ba'aretz asher ya'aseh tov
velo yecheta. I have no idea. I'm not here to judge you,
but like nobody is perfect. So whatever it is, that's what it's
for. Okay. תנו רבנן כשחלה רבי אליעזר נכנסו ארבעה זקנים לבקרו. tanu
rabanan kshechalah Rabbi Eliezer nichnasu arba'ah zkenim levakro. Four elders came to
visit him. So רבי טרפון ורבי יהושע ורבי אלעזר בן עזריה ורבי
עקיבא. Rabbi Tarfon v'Rabbi Yehoshua v'Rabbi Elazar ben Azarya v'Rabbi Akiva. So
now they're not
תלמידים, talmidim, they're זקנים, zkenim, although some of these are his colleagues,
right? רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua is his colleague, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
is still his תלמיד. talmid. So it's very interesting. Is it framing
him as a colleague or is it framing him as a
תלמיד? talmid? Where were we? Okay. נענה רבי טרפון ואמר טוב אתה
לישראל מטיפה של גשמים. ne'enah Rabbi Tarfon v'amar tov atah l'Yisrael mitipa
shel gshamim. You are better to the Jewish people than the rain.
You give life to the Jewish people.
Okay. מטיפה של גשמים. mitipa shel gshamim. שטיפה של גשמים בעולם הזה.
shetipa shel gshamim b'olam hazeh. You give rain is only good in
this world. ורבי בעולם הזה ובעולם הבא. v'rabbi b'olam hazeh u'v'olam habah.
You give good to the Jewish people in this world and you'll
be up there and you'll either receive your reward in the world
to come, or you'll be a מליץ יושר meilitz yosher for us
in the world to come. Of course, it's also pointing the fact
that we're pretty much expecting you to be going to the world
to come. Okay, but anyway. All right. So okay. But it shows
how much we value you and we sort of think you as
etc. So
where
were we? Okay. בעולם הזה ובעולם הבא. b'olam hazeh u'v'olam habah. נענה
רבי יהושע ואמר טוב אתה לישראל יותר מגלגל של חמה. ne'enah Rabbi
Yehoshua v'amar tov atah l'Yisrael yoter migalgal shel chamah. You're better than
the sun. שגלגל חמה בעולם הזה. shegalgal chamah b'olam hazeh. It's only
in this world. ורבי בעולם הזה ובעולם הבא. v'rabbi b'olam hazeh u'v'olam
habah. The world to come. Okay. So we need rain, we need
sunlight. You're our sun. You're our... נענה רבי אלעזר בן עזריה ואמר
טוב אתה לישראל יותר מאב ואם. ne'enah Rabbi Elazar ben Azarya v'amar
tov atah l'Yisrael yoter m'av v'em. You're more than parents, mother and
father. Interesting, nice that they mention אם. em. שאב ואם בעולם הזה.
she'av v'em b'olam hazeh. ורבי בעולם הזה ובעולם הבא. v'rabbi b'olam hazeh
u'v'olam habah. נענה רבי עקיבא. ne'enah Rabbi Akiva. You're always waiting for
what Rabbi Akiva is going to change the whole conversation, right? נענה
רבי עקיבא ואמר חביבין יסורין. ne'enah Rabbi Akiva v'amar chavivin yisurin. Hey,
it's good that you're like King Lear. Yeah, it's good you should
appreciate the fact that you're suffering. So there he was, he was
clearly suffering. They thought that they were going to alleviate his suffering
by having them talk about how valuable they found him. Okay, but
how does that help him in terms of his current suffering? It's
all very nice to hear first of all you're eulogizing me, I'm
not dead yet. Okay, and how does that help me in terms
of how I'm experiencing the suffering? So Rabbi Akiva comes and says
something shocking and not just also it's not also like a little
I mean I'm not saying that what they were saying is trite
but you know but it's not just like what you expect somebody
to say and it catches his attention. So he says, אמר להם
סמכוני. amar lahem samchuni. Wait, wait. You know, pick me up like
like lift me up. Wait, wait. You know, you're lying flat. Wait
a minute. Like help me get help me you know support me
a little bit. דאשמע דברי עקיבא תלמידי. d'eshma divrei Akiva talmidi. I
want to hear what Akiva my student has to say here. He's
saying something interesting. He's not saying what you guys are saying. You
guys are saying I can get in a Hallmark card. I want
to see what he's saying. שאמר חביבין יסורין. she'amar chavivin yisurin. Now
he says יסורין yisurin are very dear. אמר לו עקיבא זו מנין
לך? amar lo Akiva zu minayin lach? Where do you get this
from? אמר מקרא אני דורש. amar mikra ani doreish. I learned it
from a פסוק. pasuk. בן שתים עשרה שנה מנשה במלכו וחמש וחמשים
שנה מלך בירושלים ויעש הרע בעיני ה'. ben shtem esreh shanah Menashe
b'molcho v'chamishim v'chamesh shanah malach b'Yerushalayim vaya'as hara b'einei Hashem. He did
the evil in God's eyes. What? He's among the
truly...
Right,
he is the longest ruling king and he
did
evil. וכתיב u'chtiv and
it says, גם אלה משלי שלמה אשר העתיקו אנשי חזקיהו מלך יהודה.
gam eleh mishlei Shlomo asher hetiku anshei Chizkiyahu melech Yehudah. That Chizkiyahu
basically wrote over Mishlei. Chizkiyahu was Menashe's
father. וחזקיהו מלך יהודה לכל העולם כולו לימד תורה ולמנשה בנו לא
לימד תורה? v'Chizkiyahu melech Yehudah l'chol olam kulo limed Torah u'l'Menashe bno
lo limed Torah? Do you think he taught everybody Mishlei and he
didn't teach it to Menashe his son? He obviously taught his son
as well. And Mishlei has all these lessons of how to live
a good life. And did it do any good that he taught
his son all these lessons? No. So
אלא מכל תורך שטרח בו מכל עמל שעמל בו. ela mikol torach
shetarach bo mikol amal she'amal bo. No matter how much Chizkiyahu tried
to give Menashe a good upbringing, okay, לא העלו למוטב. lo he'elu
l'mutav. And nothing did it to put Menashe on the straight and
arrow. אלא יסורין. ela yisurin. The one thing that set Menashe straight
was the suffering. שנאמר shene'emar as it says,
וידבר ה' אל מנשה ואל עמו ולא הקשיבו ויבא ה' עליהם את
שרי הצבא אשר למלך אשור, vayidaber Hashem el Menashe v'el amo v'lo
hikshivu vayave Hashem aleihem et sarei hatzava asher l'melech Ashur, brought the
troops of the kings of Ashur. וילכדו את מנשה בחוחים vayilkdu et
Menashe bachochim and they were victorious over Menashe. ויאסרהו בנחשתים vayisruhu b'nechushtayim
and they bound him in chains of
copper. ויוליכוהו. vayolichuhu. אלוקיו Elokav and
he
subjugated himself greatly before the God of his
fathers. ויפלל אליו Vayipalel elav and he
prayed to him, ויעתר לו, vayeitar lo, and he, you know, he
beseeched him, וישמע תחינתו, vayishma tkhinato, and God listened to his prayer,
וישיבהו ירושלים למלכותו, vayishivehu Yerushalayim lemalkhuto, and He returned him to Jerusalem
to his kingdom, וידע מנשה כי השם הוא האלקים. vayeida Menashe ki
Hashem hu ha'Elokim. הלמדנו שחביבין ייסורין, Halamadnu shekhavivin yisurin, you see how
dear they are. Now of course that's like wait, that's worse than
the previous message. The previous message was I'm suffering because of something
I did wrong in this world, fine, okay, so it's something I'm
but nobody's perfect I did something wrong. But the ייסורין yisurin of
מנשה Menashe is for somebody who was wicked to wake them up
to their wickedness to get them to do good. So how is
he now saying that as the proof to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
of חביבין ייסורין? khavivin yisurin? I have no idea here how that's
supposed to now become a relevant message, a relevant and an uplifting
message. I don't know what to say about that. Anyway but it
is very parallel. The גמרא Gemara has a great line, it says
when it says ויסר המלך את טבעתו מעל ידו ויתנה להמן, Vayasar
hamalech et taba'ato mei'al yado vayitnah le'Haman, right? So the גמרא Gemara
says that act of handing over the signet ring did more than
all the words of all the prophets in order to get the
people to do תשובה, teshuvah, okay which is the same point, right?
The fear of the impending evil is much more effective right than
all the מוסר mussar that you're hearing when things are going good
or whatever, you know, when you're not sort of fearing the consequences.
Okay let's just finish to the two dots. תנו רבנן שלושה באו
בעלילה, Tanu rabanan shlosha bau ba'alila, three people came with like a
complaint to God, אלו הן, elu hein, and they weren't just praying
to God they were coming like with like a sense of like
a righteous complaint: קין עשו ומנשה. Kayin Esav u'Menashe. קין דכתיב גדול
עוני מנשוא, Kayin dekhitiv gadol avoni minaso, my sin is too burden
or my punishment is too great to bear. אמר לפניו רבונו של
עולם, Amar lefanav Ribono Shel Olam, so he's asking God what, גדול
עוני מנשוא, gadol avoni minaso, is my sin greater מששים ריבוא mishishim
ribo who are going to sin with the חטא העגל? chet ha'eigel?
You have six hundred thousand who are going to sin with the
חטא העגל chet ha'eigel and you are going to forgive them, me
you can't forgive? ואתה סולח להם? Ve'ata soleiach lahem? Okay and therefore
it's not just please God forgive me it's like you better like
you know how could you not forgive me, like you know challenging
God. עשו דכתיב הברכה אחת היא לך אבי, Esav dekhitiv habracha achat
hi lecha avi, so that's not challenging God but it's coming with
a טענה: taina: what, you only have one ברכה? bracha? Give me
the ברכה bracha I deserve.
מנשה בתחילה קרא לאלהות הרבה ולבסוף קרא לאלהי אבותיו. Menashe batkhila kara
l'elohoot harbei u'levasof kara l'elohei avotav. At first he was calling all
the other gods and then he called to the God of his
fathers. So how is that actually coming with like a challenge or
complaint? Not exactly clear how that sort of fits in to the
to the theme here. רש״י Rashi says like, it says like he
only prayed to God after everything else didn't work out. But still
so I guess it's more like oh I think the point is
like God you better answer me because if you don't answer me
it's going to prove that you're not you know that you're just
as bad as all these other gods. So because he tried all
the other gods and it didn't work there's an implicit almost like
ultimatum in the praying to God. אברהם אבינו, Avraham Avinu, there you
go. I'll just read one more sentence we'll end with that. אבא
שאול אומר אף ההוגה את השם באותיותיו, Abba Shaul omer af hahogeh
et Hashem be'otiyotav, if somebody articulates God's name the way it is
spelled. תנא ובגבולין ובלשון עגה, Tana u'vigvulin u'vilshon agah, only if you
do it outside of the Temple and לשון עגה lashon agah is
not exactly clear but like there's a vernacular you don't do it
in Hebrew somehow maybe if you do it in Hebrew it makes
it better even though it's outside the Temple I don't really get
it exactly. Anyway we will end with this and we'll pick up
here tomorrow.
On מנשה Menashe
his...